# Michael Xieyang Liu

Human-Computer Interaction Institute, School of Computer Science Carnegie Mellon University 5000 Forbes Avenue Pittsburgh, PA 15213

## RESEARCH FOCUS

My research is at the intersection of human-computer interaction (HCI), programming tools, sensemaking, intelligent user interfaces, and human-AI interaction, where I design and build systems that accelerate online sensemaking for developers and facilitate human-AI interactions for end-users.

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. in Human-Computer Interaction (in progress)

2017 - 2023 (expected)

Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, USA

Thesis: Scaffolding Knowledge Capturing, Structuring, and Reuse during Online Sensemaking

Advisors: Brad A. Myers, Aniket Kittur

Committee: Kenneth Holstein (CMU HCII), Daniel M. Russell (Google, Inc.)

M.S. in Human-Computer Interaction

2017 - 2021

Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, USA

**B.S. in Computer Science** 

2013 - 2017

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Peer-reviewed Conference Papers

Michael Xieyang Liu, Advait Sarkar, Carina Negreanu, Ben Zorn, Jack Williams, Neil Toronto, Andrew D. Gordon. "What It Wants Me To Say": Bridging the Abstraction Gap Between End-User Programmers

C12. and Code-Generating Large Language Models. Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2023).

**Q** Best Paper Honorable Mention Award

Tianying Chen, Michael Xieyang Liu, Emily Ding, Emma O'Neil, Mansi Agarwal, Robert E. Kraut, Laura C11. Dabbish. Facilitating Counselor Reflective Learning With a Real-time Annotation Tool. Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2023).

Michael Xieyang Liu, Andrew Kuznetsov, Yongsung Kim, Joseph Chee Chang, Aniket Kittur, Brad A.

C10. Myers. Wigglite: Low-cost Information Collection and Triage. Proceedings of the 35th Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2022).

Franklin Mingzhe Li, Michael Xieyang Liu, Yang Zhang, Patrick Carrington. Freedom to Choose: Understanding Input Modality Preferences of People with Upper-body Motor Impairments for

C9. Activities of Daily Living. Proceedings of the 24th International ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS 2022).

Michael Xieyang Liu, Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers. Crystalline: Lowering the Cost for Developers to Collect and Organize Information for Decision Making. Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2022).

- Amber Horvath, Michael Xieyang Liu, River Hendriksen, Connor Shannon, Emma Paterson, Kazi Jawad,
- C7. Andrew Macvean, Brad A. Myers. Understanding How Programmers Can Use Annotations on **Documentation**. Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2022).
  - Michael Xieyang Liu, Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers. To Reuse or Not To Reuse? A Framework and System for Evaluating Summarized Knowledge. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction.
- C6. 5, CSCW1, Article 166 (April 2021) (CSCW 2021).
  - TBest Paper Award and CMU SCS News Coverage
  - Joseph Chee Chang, Yongsung Kim, Victor Miller, Michael Xieyang Liu, Brad A. Myers, Aniket Kittur.
- C5. Tabs.do: Task-Centric Browser Tab Management. Proceedings of the 34th Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2021).
  - Alex Reinhart, Logan Brooks, Maria Jahja, Aaron Rumack, Jingjing Tang, [et al., including Michael
- Xieyang Liu]. An open repository of real-time COVID-19 indicators. Proceedings of the National C4. Academy of Sciences (PNAS 2021).
  - **CMU COVIDCast Website**
  - Michael Xieyang Liu, Jane Hsieh, Nathan Hahn, Angelina Zhou, Emily Deng, Shaun Burley, Cynthia
- Taylor, Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers. Unakite: Scaffolding Developers' Decision-Making Using the Web. C3. Proceedings of the 32nd Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2019). **Q** Best Paper Honorable Mention Award
  - Jean Y. Song, Stephan J. Lemmer, Michael Xieyang Liu, Shiyan Yan, Juho Kim, Jason J. Corso, Walter S.
- Lasecki. Popup: Reconstructing 3D Video Using Particle Filtering to Aggregate Crowd Responses. Proceedings of the 24th Annual ACM International Conference on Intelligent UserInterfaces (IUI 2019).
- Yu-Wei Chao, Yunfan Liu, Xieyang Liu, Huayi Zeng, Jia Deng. Learning to Detect Human-Object C1. Interactions. 2018 IEEE Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV 2018).

#### **Workshop Papers & Posters**

- Jane Hsieh, Michael Xieyang Liu, Brad A. Myers, Aniket Kittur. An Exploratory Study of Web Foraging W3. to Understand and Support Programming Decisions. IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages and
- Human-Centric Computing (VL/HCC 2018).
  - Michael Xieyang Liu, Nathan Hahn, Angelina Zhou, Shaun Burley, Emily Deng, Aniket Kittur, Brad A.
- Myers. UNAKITE: Support Developers for Capturing and Persisting Design Rationales When Solving W2. Problems Using Web Resources. DTSHPS'18 Workshop on Designing Technologies to Support Human Problem Solving, IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages and Human-Centric Computing (VL/HCC 2018).
  - Michael Xieyang Liu, Shaun Burley, Emily Deng, Angelina Zhou, Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers.
- Supporting Knowledge Acceleration for Programming from a Sensemaking Perspective. Sensemaking Workshop @ CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2018).

#### **Patent**

- Ben Zorn, Carina Negreanu, Advait Sarkar, Andrew Gordon, Jack Williams, Michael Xievang Liu, Neil
- P2. Toronto, Sruti Srinivasa Ragavan. Generation of Interactive Utterances of Code Tasks. US Patent (submitted), 2022
- Aniket Kittur, Brad A. Myers, Michael Xieyang Liu. Multidirectional Gesturing for OnDisplay Item P1. Identification and/or Further Action Control. US Patent PCT/US2022/043604 (submitted), 2022

## **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

Microsoft Research, Research Intern

May - Aug. 2022

with Advait Sarkar, Carina Negreanu, Jack Williams, Andy Gordon, Ben Zorn

Designed, built, and evaluated natural language interactions for end-user programmers by leveraging code-generating large language models (LLMs).

Google, UX Research Intern

May - Aug. 2020

with Dustin Smith, Todd Kulesza, and Sarah D'Angelo

Conducted qualitative research on Go developers' refactoring practices and engagement with refactoring tools.

Bosch Research, Research Intern

May - Aug. 2019

with Lisa Yu, Wan-Yi Lin, and Alessandro Oltramari

Worked on crowd & AI-powered projects that aim to improve the safety and performance of autonomous vehicles.

## **OPEN-SOURCE EXPERIENCE**

**Vertical Tabs Chrome Extension** 

2019 - present

30,000+ users on Chrome Web Store; 370+ ★ on GitHub (as of Apr. 2023)

Chrome extension boilerplate (w/ React & Webpack)

2019 - present

2,200+ ★, 750+ ♥ on GitHub (as of Apr. 2023); powering startups such as HyperWrite AI

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant (advised by Brad A. Myers & Aniket Kittur)

2017 - present

Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University

Working on prototype systems that scaffold developers in making decisions using information from various web sources and enable subsequent developers to learn, understand, and reuse those decisions and rationales.

Research Assistant (with Jodi Forlizzi, Roni Rosenfeld & Ryan Tibshirani)

2020 - 2021

Delphi Research Group, Carnegie Mellon University

Working on the visualization team of the COVIDcast system, which displays indicators related to COVID-19 activity level across the U.S. These indicators are derived from a variety of anonymized, aggregated data sources made available by multiple partners, including Facebook, Google, and Quidel. [Press coverage]

#### Undergraduate Researcher

2016 - 2017

Crowds and Machines Lab, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Worked on crowd & AI-powered interdisciplinary projects that address novel and promising research questions.

#### Research Assistant (advised by Jia Deng)

2015 - 2016

Vision & Learning Lab, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Worked on a computer vision based toolkit that boosts performance on human-object interaction detection by exploiting human-object spatial relations.

## **Invited Talks**

 $\label{lem:continuous} Accelerating \ Programming \ Sense making \ with \ Human-Centered \ Interactive \ Systems$ 

Mar. 2023

Apple AI/ML

Microsoft Research

Accelerating Sensemaking with Human-Centered Interactive Systems  Google Research	Feb. 2023
Allen Institute for Artificial Intelligence (AI2)	
Bridging the Abstration Gap Between End-User Programmers and LLM-backed Code-Generating Models  Microsoft Research	Aug. 2022
Understanding Refactoring with Golang	Aug. 2020
Google Cloud DevEx Presentation	8
Supporting Knowledge Acceleration for Programming from a Sensemaking Perspective	April 2018
Sensemaking Workshop at CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems	
SELECTED HONORS, GRANTS, AWARDS & COVERAGE	
<b>Best Paper Honorable Mention Award</b> , ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2023)	April 2023
<b>Special Recognitions for Outstanding Reviews</b> , ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2023)	Nov. 2022
CMU SCS News Coverage on our CSCW 2021 Best Paper: "CMU Researchers Develop Tool To Help Determine When To Reuse Content"	Nov. 2021
<b>Best Paper Award</b> , 24th ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW 2021)	Oct. 2021
<b>Special Recognitions for Outstanding Reviews</b> , 34th Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2021)	June 2021
<b>CMU News Coverage on COVIDcast</b> : "Carnegie Mellon Unveils Five Interactive COVID-19 Maps"	April 2020
<b>Best Paper Honorable Mention Award</b> , 32nd Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2019)	Oct. 2019
SHF: Small: Knowledge Acceleration for Programming (\$500,000 over 3 years), NSF	June 2018
James B. Angell Scholar, 94th Annual Honors Convocation, University of Michigan	March 2017
EECS Scholar Award, 2017 EECS Honors & Awards Reception, University of Michigan	March 2017
Summer Undergraduate Research Experience (SURE) program, University of Michigan	May 2016
Tang-Junyuan Fellowship (Top 2/250, \$50,000), UM-SJTU Joint Institute	July 2015, July 2016
Dean's List, University of Michigan	Dec. 2015, April 2016
Basic Teaching Assistant Certificate, Center for Learning and Teaching, UM-SJTU Joint Institute	Aug. 2015
Dean's List, UM-SJTU Joint Institute	2013 - 2015
Fellowship for Outstanding Academic Performance, Shanghai Jiao Tong University	June 2015
Meritorious Winner (Acceptance: 9%), COMAP Mathematical Contest in Modeling	April 2015
MENTOPING	

## **MENTORING**

Jane Hsieh 2018 - 2019

Oberlin College Student (Currently a CMU S3D Ph.D. Candidate)

Studied programmers' web-foraging behaviors. Contributed to the development of the Unakite system.

Emily Deng 2017 - 2018

CMU Master's Student

Designed and carried out interview studies with programmers that probe their programming behaviors and needs.

Shaun Burley 2017 - 2018

CMU Master's Student

Designed and carried out interview studies with programmers that probe their programming behaviors and needs.

## **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

Teaching Assistant – 05-410/05-610 User-Centered Research & Evaluation Fall 2020

Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University

Teaching Assistant – 05-431/05-631 Software Structures for User Interfaces Fall 2020

Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University

Teaching Assistant – 05-430/05-630 Programming Usable Interfaces Fall 2019

Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University

Instructional Aide – EECS484 Database Management Systems Winter 2017

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Instructional Aide – EECS484 Database Management Systems Fall 2016

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Teaching Assistant - Vv255 Multivariate Calculus

University of Michigan - Shanghai Jiao Tong University Joint Institute

## **SERVICE**

#### **Academic Service**

**Associate Chair** ACM CHI 2020 Late Breaking Work Track

Conferences: CHI (2019 - 2023), CSCW (2019 - 2023), UIST (2019 - 2022), IUI (2020,

2023), **VAST** (2020)

Paper Reviewing Journal: TOCHI (2022)

**Q** Special Recognitions for Outstanding Reviews: **UIST** (2021), **CHI** (2023)

#### Departmental & Community Service

Committee Member Ph.D. Admission committee (2022-2023)

Committee Member REU (Research Experience for Undergraduate) Admissions Committee (2021-2022)

Committee Member CMU HCII Faculty Lunch Organization Committee (2019-2020)

Committee Member CMU HCII Ph.D. Student Lounge Committee (2019-2020)

## LANGUAGES, TECHNICAL SKILLS & COURSES

Languages English, Chinese (Mandarin) - Native or bilingual proficiency,

German - Limited working proficiency

ProgrammingHTML/Javascript/CSS, Python, SQL, C/C++, Swift, Java, LaTeX, etc.Web & App DevelopmentReact.js, Angular, Redux, Bootstrap, Node.js, PHP, Ionic Framework, etc.

**Deep Learning & AI** PyTorch, Tensorflow, ml5.js

Courses Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Advanced User Interfaces, Database Management

Systems, Information Security, Web Development

Summer 2015

## **REFERENCES**

#### Brad A. Myers (doctoral advisor)

Professor & Director of HCII

 $Human\ Computer\ Interaction\ Institute,\ School\ of\ Computer\ Science,\ Carnegie\ Mellon\ University\ bam@cs.cmu.edu$ 

#### Aniket (Niki) Kittur (doctoral advisor)

Professor

Human Computer Interaction Institute, School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University nkittur@cs.cmu.edu

#### Ben Zorn

Partner Researcher & Former Co-manager of the Research in Software Engineering (RiSE) Microsoft Research, Redmond, US ben.zorn@microsoft.com

#### Advait Sarkar

Senior Researcher Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK advait@microsoft.com

#### **Andy Gordon**

Senior Principal Research Manager Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK adg@microsoft.com

#### Carina Negreanu

Senior Researcher Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK cnegreanu@microsoft.com